Hi, this is Matt Baker. Today, I'm going
to give you a brief introduction to Old
Testament Textual Criticism, similar to
what I did last year for the New
Testament. Once again, I'll be using
this chart, which was made by a
colleague of mine named Stephen Nelson
from Crossway Bible. It makes a great
companion chart to my own timeline of
biblical composition. You see, whereas
my chart covers who wrote each book of
the Bible and when, the Crossway Bible
chart covers what manuscripts have been
discovered and how these have been used
to piece together the final text. So,
together you get the entire history of
the Bible from its very first authors to
the modern English translations
available today. The chart on the right,
which is the one we'll be looking at
today, is available via the online Bible
study platform crosswaybible.com,
whereas the one on the left is available
on our own website usefulcharts.com.
Links to both are available in the
description and pinned comment.
Okay, let's now dive into textual
criticism. First of all, please remember
that textual criticism is not about
promoting a negative view of the Bible.
It's simply the process that scholars
use when trying to figure out what was
most likely the original wording of the
Bible. You see, there are no original
manuscripts available for any book of
the Bible. All we have are copies of
copies of copies of the originals. And
the thing is, when we compare all of the
various copies that we have, we find
differences called textual variants,
thousands of them. Now, most of the time
these differences are quite minor, but
still, they are different. So, the
question comes up, which version is most
likely to be closest to the original?
Well, that's where textual criticism
comes in. Last time I mentioned two of
the most important principles of textual
criticism. The first is that older
variants are usually assumed to be
closer to the original. This is because
we know that given more time, the
chances of something being changed,
either deliberately or by mistake, goes
up. The second is that the shorter and
more awkward sounding a variant is, the
more likely it is to be the original.
This is because when editors do make
changes, it's often to make things more
clear. And to make things more clear,
additional words are often required.
Now, to these two principles, I'm going
to add a third, and that is that
readings preserved in the original
language are traditionally favored over
those found in translations. This is
pretty obvious because if you've ever
done any translation work, you'll know
that it's impossible to ever translate
anything perfectly from one language to
another language.
Okay, so let's now dive into the chart.
As I mentioned last time, each colored
square represents an actual manuscript
that has been found, and the column it's
placed in represents the century that it
has been dated to. Now, most of this
chart covers the New Testament. If you
want to see the explanation for that
part, I'll leave a link in the
description to the previous video.
Today, we'll be concentrating only on
the very top portion, which covers the
Old Testament. Now, usually when talking
about this part of the Bible, I prefer
to use the term Hebrew Bible or Tanakh,
which is the Jewish term. But, in this
video, I'm mostly going to use Old
Testament because some of what we'll be
discussing goes beyond what is included
in the Jewish Tanakh. So, when it comes
to the Old Testament, we can divide all
of the various sources we have into
three main textual families, known as
text types. There's the Hebrew Masoretic
Text, abbreviated MT, the Greek
Septuagint, abbreviated LXX, and finally
the Samaritan Pentateuch, or SP. Take
note of the color scheme. Brown for
Masoretic, pale green for Septuagint,
and gray for Samaritan, because that's
what's going to be used throughout the
chart to indicate what text type each
source belongs to. Now, one thing we
know for sure is that most of the Old
Testament was originally written in
classical Hebrew, which was in use from
around 1000 BCE to roughly 200 BCE.
Well, the only one of these three text
types that transmits the full Hebrew
Bible in that original language is the
Masoretic text. So, according to
principle three, that would make it the
most likely to be closest to the
original. However, there's a problem. As
we're about to see, the oldest
Septuagint copies that we have, which
remember are Greek translations, are
much, much older than the oldest
Masoretic copies that we have. And
therefore, according to principle one,
it would be the Septuagint manuscripts
that would be most likely to be the
closest to the original. So, in other
words, we've got two principles at odds
with each other. As for the Samaritan
Pentateuch, it's written in a later
dialect of classical Hebrew, and we
don't have any very old manuscripts for
it, so it's usually not seen as being a
contender for representing the original.
Okay, so with those basics under our
belts, let me now talk in greater detail
about the Masoretic text. If you pick up
any copy of a modern Jewish Bible with
Hebrew in it, what you'll be looking at
is the Masoretic text. So, for example,
this is my own copy of the JPS Tanakh,
JPS standing for Jewish Publication
Society. On one side is the Hebrew
Masoretic text, and on the other side is
an English translation. If you don't
have a Jewish Bible at home, that's not
a problem, because you can just go to
sefaria.org,
which is a free online library of all
the major Jewish texts. So, for example,
if you click on Tanakh, what you'll get
is Masoretic on one side and English on
the other. Now, Crossway Bible, the
maker of the chart I'm using today,
actually does something similar, except
that it allows you to add up to three
different English translations beside
the Masoretic. And then, of course,
another place you'll find the Masoretic
text is in every Jewish synagogue in the
world. That's because just about every
synagogue has a handwritten Torah
scroll. The Torah being the first five
books of the Tanakh. Every Torah scroll
is an exact copy of the first part of
the Masoretic text. So, how old is the
oldest copy we have of the Masoretic
text? Well, it's not as old as you might
think. The oldest complete copy still in
existence is the Leningrad Codex, which
dates to around 1,000 years ago. Now,
1,000 years ago is pretty old, but
considering that the Hebrew Bible was
written about 2,500 years ago, that
doesn't actually bring us that close to
the original. The Aleppo Codex and the
Codex Sassoon 1053 are a bit older, but
both of those are only partial copies,
as is Codex Cairensis. Now, the reason
why the Masoretic text is called
Masoretic is because it was preserved
and standardized by a group of Jewish
scribes called the Masoretes. They were
responsible for adding the vowel markers
that are used to this day. And as you
can see here, they started making copies
of the Hebrew Bible as far back as 600
CE. Now, where did they get their
initial copy from? Well, we don't know,
but the assumption is that they must
have used copies that were based on
copies that were based on copies that go
all the way back to around the year 400
BCE, which is probably around the time
that most of the Old Testament books
reached their final form. These
hypothetical copies that existed around
that time, upon which the later
Masoretic text was based, are often
called proto-Masoretic texts. But here's
the thing, these proto-Masoretic texts
were not the only version of the Old
Testament that existed at that time.
Prior to the 3rd century BCE, there was
also a slightly different version of the
Old Testament floating around, labeled
here as the Proto-Septuagint,
which is the hypothetical Hebrew source
that the so-called Old Greek Septuagint
was based on. Now, take note that I may
also use the word Septuagints,
plural, rather than Septuagint,
singular. A lot of people assume that
there was just one official Septuagint
created at just one point in time. But
this is not the case. There were
actually multiple Greek translations of
the Hebrew Bible made over several
centuries, all of which tend to be
collectively referred to as the
Septuagint. You see, over time certain
Jewish scholars, such as Aquila,
Symmachus, and Theodotion, produced
revised Greek versions that brought the
text into closer alignment with the
emerging standard Hebrew text that we
now refer to as proto-Masoretic. So,
when scholars talk about the Septuagint,
we sometimes need to clarify when this
refers to the old Greek version as
opposed to the later revised versions
that are closer to the Masoretic.
According to legend, the first Greek
translation was created in the 3rd
century BCE and consisted only of the
Torah, or Pentateuch. As the legend
goes, Ptolemy II of Egypt invited 72
Jewish scholars to translate the Hebrew
Torah into Greek for the first time
ever, so that a copy could be stored in
the famous Library of Alexandria. The 72
was eventually simplified as 70, hence
the name Septuagint, which in Greek
literally means 70. Over the next 100
years, the remaining books of the Tanakh
were translated as well, probably
several times by several different
groups. And hence, by the time of Jesus,
several different Septuagints were in
circulation. This is important because
by the 1st century CE, Aramaic had
largely replaced Hebrew as the main
spoken language in Judea, while Greek
was also widely used, especially by the
educated class and in the diaspora,
which is why most of the Old Testament
quotations found in the New Testament
match better with the Old Greek version
of the Septuagint than with the
Masoretic text. Now, like I mentioned
earlier, we have several surviving
copies of the Septuagint that are much
older than the medieval Masoretic
copies. Most notably, these include
Codex Sinaiticus and Codex Vaticanus,
both of which date to around the 4th
century CE. So, that's at least 600
years older than the Masoretic text.
They are both mentioned down here in the
New Testament section, as they also
include near complete versions of the
Greek New Testament. Okay, at this
point, I should explain some of the main
differences between the Masoretic text
and the Septuagint. After all, it's
because of these differences that we
know that there were at least two
slightly different early versions of the
Old Testament. So, first of all, there
are some really big differences
involving entire books. The best example
is Jeremiah. Basically, the Septuagint
has a totally different version of
Jeremiah. Not only is it 12% shorter,
several chapters also appear in an
entirely different order. Then, there's
Esther. In this case, it's the Masoretic
version that's shorter. And what's
really interesting is that Masoretic
Esther makes no mention of God, not even
once. Whereas Septuagint Esther not only
mentions God, but includes several
prayers and other theological elements.
So yeah, that's a pretty big difference.
Other books that differ in terms of
length and content include 1 Samuel,
Ezekiel, Psalms, Proverbs, Job, and
Daniel. And then of course there's the
fact that the Septuagint includes a few
extra books from the broader Jewish
tradition that are entirely missing from
the Hebrew Masoretic text, such as Tobit
and Judith. But take note that most of
the major differences involve either the
Prophets section or the Writings
section. Generally speaking, the Torah
or Pentateuch is much closer in both the
Septuagint and in the Masoretic text.
The one main exception to this is the
genealogies found in Genesis 5 and 11.
When we compare the numbers given in
both texts, we can see that the
Septuagint pushes back the date for
Adam's creation by about 1,400 years.
I'll come back to this a bit later. But
first, I want to point out that in
addition to these larger differences
involving entire books and chapters,
there are also thousands of smaller
verse-level differences involving things
like spelling, phrasing, and word
choice. The two most well-known because
they impact theology are Psalm 22:16
and Isaiah 7:14. Let's look at the one
in Psalms first, which is often listed
as verse 17 in the Masoretic text. In
the Masoretic text, the verse reads,
"For many dogs have surrounded me. A
band of evildoers has encircled me.
They, like a lion, are at my hands and
my feet." But in the Septuagint, it
reads, "For many dogs have surrounded
me. A A of evildoers has encircled me.
They dug into my hands and my feet. With
most English versions translating dug
into as pierced. Obviously, choosing the
word pierced brings to mind the
crucifixion. And it's therefore the
translation preferred by Christians who
see this verse as being a prophecy. Some
Christians even go as far as to say that
sometime after the death of Jesus,
Jewish scribes deliberately changed this
verse in order to hide the obvious
allusion to Jesus. On the flip side,
some Jews claim that it was the
Christians who deliberately changed the
verse in order to fake a reference to
Jesus. Again, I'll come back to this a
bit later. Let's now look at Isaiah
7:14, which in the Masoretic reads, "The
Lord himself will give you a sign. The
young woman will conceive and bear a
son." Whereas the Septuagint reads, "The
Lord himself will give you a sign. The
virgin will conceive and bear a son."
Again, Christians see this as being a
prophecy about Jesus. Whereas Jews see
it as having a contemporary meaning
only. Arguing that the Hebrew word for
young woman does not necessarily imply
virginity. Although it's important to
keep in mind that even if the original
author did mean to imply virginity, this
doesn't necessarily mean that it's a
prophecy about Jesus. He could have been
simply referring to a contemporary woman
that was about to get married, get
pregnant, and have a child. So, in this
case, I think that how a person
interprets the verse will boil down to
his or her already held faith positions.
Now, at this point, I want to say a few
things about the Samaritan Pentateuch.
First of all, take note that as the name
implies, it only includes the
Pentateuch, not the entire Old
Testament. Second, generally speaking,
it tends to agree more with the
Septuagint than with with Masoretic,
which is why it's shown here as being
potentially based on a source that had
the same parent text as the Septuagint.
Third, its distinct Samaritan form
likely took shape somewhere here between
250 BCE and 50 BCE. Like I said earlier,
its final form is written in a dialect
of ancient Hebrew that is later than
that of the Masoretic text, one that was
used around this time. Now, the
Samaritans themselves claim that they
are the descendants of the northern
kingdom of Israel, which fell to the
Assyrians back in 721 BCE, and that
their version of the Pentateuch dates to
before this time. However, if we move
over to the timeline of biblical
composition, you can see that, according
to critical scholars, the vast majority
of the Old Testament was actually
written after 721, meaning that their
claim cannot be true. In fact, if we
accept the hypothesis that the
Pentateuch was written in layers, as
opposed to all at once, whether it's the
documentary hypothesis, the
supplementary hypothesis, or something
else, all of which I've covered in my
intro to the Bible series, it's almost
certain that the final version of the
Pentateuch was compiled no earlier than
458 BCE, sometime after the construction
of the Second Temple. So, who are the
Samaritans then, if not the descendants
of the northern kingdom of Israel? Well,
the leading theory is that they were
originally those referred to in Ezra and
Nehemiah as the people in the land,
meaning those who were never exiled to
Babylon, which likely included some
lower-class Judahites, some descendants
of the northern Israelites who had moved
south after the fall of Samaria, as well
as some newcomers who had been settled
there by foreign powers. We know from
both the Bible and from archaeology that
this group built a temple at Mount
Gerizim, which was sort of an
alternative or rival to the one in
Jerusalem and that existed from about
450 BCE to 100 BCE. So, what makes the
most sense is that the Samaritan
Pentateuch took shape in connection with
this Gerizim-centered community during
this period, which is exactly what the
chart shows. Which brings me to the most
important difference between the
Samaritan Pentateuch and the other two
text types. In the Samaritan Pentateuch,
there are several references to Mount
Gerizim, which do not appear in either
the Masoretic Text or the Septuagint.
For example, in Deuteronomy 27:4, God
commands the Israelites to set up an
altar on Mount Ebal. However, in the
Samaritan Pentateuch, it's Mount Gerizim
instead. According to most critical
scholars, it was the Samaritans who
changed the text to better suit their
current situation, rather than it being
the other way around. Unfortunately,
there's no way to know for sure and it
certainly doesn't help that the oldest
surviving copy of the Samaritan
Pentateuch, the Abisha Scroll, is very
late, dating to around the year 1250.
Okay, so all of this brings us back to
the question of which one of the other
two, the Masoretic or the Septuagint, is
more likely to reflect the original.
Well, as you probably know, in 1946, a
major discovery was made that many
thought would provide an answer to the
question. This, of course, was the
discovery of the Dead Sea Scrolls, which
turned out to include many manuscripts
of the Bible written in Hebrew that were
several centuries older than the oldest
Septuagint copies we had and over a
thousand years older than the oldest
Masoretic Text. But, here's the thing.
After all the analysis was said and
done, what scholars found was that while
most of the time the Hebrew of the Dead
Sea Scrolls matches fairly closely to
the Hebrew of the Masoretic Text,
meaning that the Masoretes and
pre-Masoretes did a pretty good job
preserving a consistent stream of
transmission, there are some instances
where certain Dead Sea Scrolls match
better with what the Hebrew parent text
behind the Old Greek Septuagint probably
looked like, which means that while we
can conclude that the framework of the
Masoretic Text is generally very close
to the earliest recoverable text and
thus very reliable, we cannot
definitively say that it is always going
to be closer to the original than the
parent text behind the Septuagint. At
the end of the day, we have to make
decisions one book at a time and often
one chapter at a time and sometimes even
one verse at a time, which is basically
the conclusion given by Emmanuel Tov in
his book Textual Criticism of the Hebrew
Bible, the most authoritative book on
the subject. So, using some of the
examples discussed so far, when it comes
to Jeremiah, it's likely that the
Septuagint version is closer to the
original and that the Masoretic version
represents a later expansion. But, when
it comes to Esther, the reverse is
likely true. And in terms of the Genesis
chronologies, I think there's a strong
argument to be made that the Septuagint
version is closer to the original. You
see, in the Septuagint, the age at which
each patriarch had their first child is
more consistent, going down slightly,
whereas in the Masoretic Text, it is
very uneven.
As I mentioned in my Biblical Chronology
video, it would appear that sometime
after the Maccabean revolt, scribes
likely altered the numbers in Genesis so
that the re-dedication of the temple
took place exactly 4,000 years after
creation. Now, don't get me wrong. I'm
not saying that the Septuagint numbers
are correct in some sort of literal way.
I'm just saying that they are probably
more likely to be the original numbers
used by the original authors of Genesis
5 and 11, probably for symbolic reasons.
Finally, let's return to Psalm 22:16.
This is an interesting case because
based on the evidence, it's possible
that neither the Masoretic text nor the
Septuagint is exactly correct. On one
hand, like a lion makes more sense
because it's a common phrase used
throughout the Hebrew Bible and it
matches with the dog metaphor. However,
in the Hebrew, there is no verb. So, it
literally reads, "Like a lion, hands and
feet." One proposed reconstruction is
that the original was actually, "They
bound my hands and feet." Because in
Hebrew, just one letter needs to be
swapped and therefore, it may have been
a scribe that did this by accident.
So, the solution is not to choose one
text type over another. What most
scholars use nowadays is a critical
edition of the Hebrew Bible, which uses
the Masoretic Leningrad Codex as its
base, but then incorporates notes about
variant readings found in the
Septuagint, Dead Sea Scrolls, Samaritan
Pentateuch, etc. The first such critical
edition was the Biblia Hebraica
published by Rudolf Kittel in 1906 with
updates in 1913 and 1937.
These are referred to as BH1, BH2, and
BH3. This was then replaced in the late
1960s with the Biblia Hebraica
Stuttgartensia
or BHS, which is named after the city of
Stuttgart because that's the location of
the German Bible Society. This is the
current critical edition used by most
Bible translators today, although it
will eventually be replaced by the
Biblia Hebraica Quinta, Quinta meaning
five. As for the Septuagint, the primary
critical edition used these days is the
Göttingen Septuagint. Now, of course, if
you don't know Hebrew and Greek, that's
not a problem because most modern Bible
translations, such as the NIV, ESV, or
NRSV, have the same kind of critical
footnotes listing major variants when
necessary so that you can be aware of
verses that can be translated in
multiple ways. You can also use websites
like crossbible.com,
which allows you to view the Masoretic,
the Septuagint, and a modern translation
all at the same time. Okay, so that was
a look at Old Testament textual
criticism. Once again, if you want to
buy a copy of the chart we've used
today, or just use it online, you can
find it at crossbible.com.
In addition to this, if you're
interested in the timeline of biblical
composition that I showed, that one is
available on our website
usefulcharts.com,
which I'll link to on the screen right
now. Thanks for watching.